Guide to the New York Architects/Frank Lupo Daniel Rowen Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
New York Architects/Frank Lupo Daniel Rowen records
1986-1997
MS 1973
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
23.33
(9 boxes)
The collection is comprised of a sampling of the work of two architects, Frank Lupo and Daniel Rowen, as well as their work together in partnership as the architecture firm New York Architects. Four major projects are represented through drawings, photographs, and job files; four additional projects are documented by sketches and presentation drawings. Lupo and Rowen, both alumni of the Yale School of Architecture, were protégés of the architect Charles Gwathmey, and formed their own partnership in 1984. Their work was largely concentrated in New York City and environs.
Rowen, Daniel Jared, 1953-2009
Biographical / Historical
In 1985, Daniel Rowen and Frank Lupo formed New York Architects, which became Lupo Rowen Architects in the early 1990s. In 1995, they formed separate sole proprietorships, Frank Lupo Architects and Daniel Rowen Architects. Lupo went on to become an associate principal at FXFOWLE Architects, and Rowen moved his practice from New York City to East Hampton, New York, in 2003.
Firm biography courtesy of Oculus.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Coco Myers and Frank Lupo, 2010.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of a sampling of the work of two architects, Frank Lupo and Daniel Rowen, as well as their work together in partnership as the architecture firm New York Architects. Four major projects are represented through drawings, photographs, and job files; four additional projects are documented by sketches and presentation drawings. Lupo and Rowen, both alumni of the Yale School of Architecture, were protégés of the architect Charles Gwathmey, and formed their own partnership in 1984. Their work was largely concentrated in New York City and environs.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arrangement is alphabetical by project name. Within each project, drawings are listed, then job files.
Architecture -- New York (State) -- New York; Architecture -- United States -- History -- 20th Century; Architecture, American -- 20th Century; Architecture, Domestic; Architecture, Modern -- 20th Century; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Lupo, Frank M.; Rowen, Daniel Jared, 1953-2009
- Project records, 1986-1997
  - Bach residence, Pound Ridge, New York
    - Drawings
      - Mylars SP1-SP2; S0-S3.1; M0-M3.2; P1-P3.1; E1-E3.1; sepias E1-E3.1, 1987-1992 (Box 1)
      - Presentation drawings, Circa 1990 (Box 2)
    - Job files
      - Contracts, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Model photographs, negatives, Circa 1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Snapshots, as-built, Circa 1994 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Transparencies, photostats, project statement, professional photographs, 1989-1994 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Lebard apartment ["The White Apartment"], New York, New York
    - Drawings
      - Original mylars and design sketches, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Job files
      - Contract, sketches, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Publicity, photographs, slides, negatives, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Specification, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - MasterZone offices, New York, New York
    - Drawings
      - Original construction drawings, 1997 (Box 4)
      - Millwork, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Job files
      - Bids, contracts, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Specification, slides, plan, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - 77 Bleecker/Lipschultz-Jones apartment, New York, New York
    - Drawings
      - Millwork, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Sketches, presentation drawings, 1986-1988 (Box 7)
      - Original mylars and construction drawings, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
    - Job files
      - Budget, permits, contract, 1986-1987 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Photostats, photographs, negatives, transparencies, Circa 1987 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Specification, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous presentation drawings
    - Dumore showroom, Long Island City, New York, Circa 1988 (Box 8)
    - 521 W. 23rd/Gagosian, New York, New York, Circa 1988 (Box 8)
    - Kreindel residence, Alpine, New Jersey: presentation, Circa 1988 (Box 8)
    - 65 Thompson/Gagosian, New York, New York, Circa 1988 (Box 8)